Meier mss., 1927-2010
Indiana University Digital Library Program
- Professional activities, 1968-2009, undated (Box 10)
  - Central Park East (CPE), 1974-2001, undated (Box 11)
    - General, 1977-2000, undated
      - Articles, 1977-2000, undated
        - On CPE, 1977-2005, undated, (4 folders)
          - Mann-Skeen, Lorraine. (1995, Aug. 14). In Schools, Small Alone Doesn't Mean Better. New York Times (p. A14). (Box 3)
          - Dash, Julehka. (1995, Oct.). Smaller, Freer, Better. The University of Chicago Magazine (p. 36)., 2 copies (Box 11)
          - (1996, Jan. 24). City Schools Can Improve; Albany Must Let Them. Newsday.
          - Mayher, Bill. (1996, Oct.). A School for These Times… Schools for Times to Come. Hope Magazine (pp. 28-37)., 5 copies
          - (1996, Oct.). Central Park East. Educational Researcher (pp. 12-13).
          - Gottlieb, Alan. (1997, May 23). Educator Likes Plan for Manual. Denver Post (pp. 1B, 4B)., 2 copies
          - Stern, Robert A. M. (2000, Jan. 22). Schools too Grand to Turn into Trash. New York Times (p. A15). (Box 3)
          - Gootman, Elissa and Herszenhorn, David M. (2005, May 3). Getting Smaller to Improve the Big Picture. New York Times (pp. B1, B4). (Box 11)
          - Untitled, undatednewspaper photograph of students with Jesse Jackson.
        - Wiseman High School II Film, 1994
          - Beale, Lewis. (1994, July 5). Wiseman Goes Back to 'School.' Daily News (p. 36).
          - Lurie, Theodora. (1994, Summer). Turning on the Power of Ideas: A new Frederick Wiseman Film Looks at a City School that Works. Ford Foundation Report, volume 25, number 2 (pp. 10-12)., 3 copies
          - Bianculli, David. (1994, Sept. 7). 'High School II' Goes to the Head of the Class. Daily News (p. 65).
          - Kempley, Rita. (1994, Sept. 7). 'High School II': Saved by the Bell. Washington Post (pp. C1, C4)., 4 copies (Box 3)
          - Mathews, Jay. (1994, Sept. 7). The Teacher Who Threw Away the Book: Debbie Meier Tore Down the Walls Standing in the Way of Learning. Washington Post (pp. C1, C4)., 4 copies
          - Bromwich, David. 1994, Sept. 19-26). Unsentimental Education: Frederick Wiseman Goes Back to School. The New Republic (pp. 39-43). (Box 11)
          - Hill, David. (1994, Sept.). Back to School. Teacher Magazine (pp. 36-39). (Box 3)
        - CPE Music Program and Music of the Heart Film, 1993-2000, undated (Box 11)
          - Gordy, Molly. (1983, June 10). Kids' Benefit Has Strings Attached. New York Newsday (p. 5).
          - Dominguez, Robert. (1999, Oct. 26). The Queen of 'Heart.' Daily News (pp. 39-41). (Box 3)
          - Hartocollis, Anemona. (1999, Oct. 27). To Celebrate Music Teacher, Film Toughened Up School (p. B9). (Box 11)
          - Garchik, Leah. (2000, Feb. 4). Setting the Musical Record Straight. San Francisco Chronicle.
          - Schorr, Jonathan. (2000, May 15). Why Did Hollywood Make 'Music of the Heart' a Solo Effort? Los Angeles Times (p. F3).
          - Reyes, Sonia. Teacher Pulls Strings. Undated.
        - Book chapters and excerpts, 1989-1995
          - Schorr, Lisbeth B. and Daniel Schorr. (1988). Within Our Reach: Breaking the Cycle of Disadvantage (pp. 241-245)., 2 copies
          - Wood, George H. (1993). Schools that Work: America's Most Innovative Public Education Programs (pp. 41-51, 165-181, 193-201, 216-220, 242-247, 265-266).
          - Bracey, Gerald W. (1995). Final Exam: A Study of the Perpetual Scrutiny of American Education.
      - David Bensam's Quality Education in the Inner City: The Story of the Central Park East Schools, 1987
        Includes draft of foreword by Ted Sizer
      - Drafts of writings by Meier on CPE and CPESS, 1987, undated
      - Curriculum planning and mailings to parents, 1985-1986, undated
      - Correspondence, 1987-1996, undated
        - Students and former students, 1987-1996, undated
        - Visitors and donors, 1989-1993
      - Photographs, undated
      - Notes and journals by Meier, 1985-1987, undated
      - Thirteen Core Beliefs, 1993
    - CPE I, CPE II, and River East, 1974-2000, undated
      - Administrative documents, 1978-1999, undated
        - Organization and scheduling notes, 1988-1989, undated
        - CPE I and II Directory, 1982-1983, (2 copies)
        - Meeting notes, memos, and correspondence with staff, 1978-1999, undated
      - Correspondence with parents, 1976-2006, undated
      - Mailings and publications, 1974-2000, undated
        - Booklets and brochures, 1985-2000, undated
        - Graduation and concert programs, 1984-1985
        - Mailings to Parents, 1974-2000, undated
          - General, 1974-2000, undated
          - On reading, undated
          - On math, undated
          - On testing, undated
        - Newsletters, 1980-2000
          - Notes, the CPE I Newsletter
          - CPE II newsletter, River East newsletter, Kids' News CPE I student newsletter, 1987-1994, 1 copy of each
      - Student work, 1983-2000, undated
        - Evaluations of students, 1983-1999
        - Student-made book for Meier, 1984, Nov. (Box 2)
        - Student Recollections books, 1997-2000 (Box 11)
      - Miscellaneous, 1975-2000, undated
        - 10th anniversary conference, 1984
          Includes invitations, program, speech by Vito Perrone
        - Graduation speeches, 1984, undated
        - Reports and proposals from CPE, 1975-1992
        - Science class transcripts, undated
        - Studies of CPE, 1984-2000, undated
    - Central Park East Secondary School (CPESS), 1984-2001, undated
      - Administrative documents, 1984-1994, undated
        - Planning documents, notes, and correspondence, 1984-1985, undated
        - Policies and handbooks, 1993, undated
        - Blank applications, undated
        - CPESS Alumni Fund for the Future donations, 1991
        - Student and staff lists, 1985-1994, undated
      - Memos and correspondence with staff, 1985-1996, undated
      - Mailings and publications, 1986-2001, undated
        - Newsletter, 1986-1994 (Box 12)
        - Mailings to parents, 1988, undated
        - Pamphlets and brochures for prospective students and families, undated
        - Reunion program, 2001
      - Student work, 1986-1991, undated
        - Collections of student work, 1986-1991, undated
        - Student magazine, 1990, undated
      - Miscellaneous, 1985-1996, undated
        - Daily Life at CPE High School, undated, (4 copies)
        - Evaluation of Meier as interim acting principal, 1989
        - Journal by CPESS teacher, 1985
        - Studies of CPESS by Naomi Barko, Donna Muncey, and Ann Lieberman, 1989-1996, undated
          Includes drafts, a publication, and correspondence
  - School reform and restructuring, 1983-2008, undated (Box 12)
    - Coalition Campus Schools Project (CCSP), 1992-1996, undated
      - Reports and papers, 1993-1995, undated
      - Articles, 1992-1995
        - Berger, Joseph. (1992, Aug. 6). Plan Seeks Small Schools with Themes: Fernandez Envisions 30 New High Schools. New York Times (pp. B1-B5), 3 copies
        - Berger, Joseph. (1992, Aug. 7). Cutting the Big High School Down to Size: Fernandez Joins the Movement to More Emphasis on Individual Teen-Agers. New York Times., 2 copies
        - Chira, Susan. (1992, Aug. 10). Harlem's Witness for the Chancellor. New York Times., 5 copies
          See also: Writings removed from binder pockets, 1 copy; Oversize 3, folder 15
        - Chiles, Nick. (1992, Oct. 20). Winners Get High Schools of Their Own. New York Newsday.
        - Willen, Liz. (1992, Oct. 20). From Vision to Reality. New York Newsday.
        - Richardson, Lynda. (1992, Oct. 20). Plans for 14 Theme High Schools Begin Taking Shape in New York. New York Times., 2 copies
        - Lee, Felicia R. (1993, Nov. 13). Bad Times Get Worse at Bronx High School as Closing Looms. New York Times. (Box 3)
        - Bradley, Ann. Project Will Divide Troubled N.Y.C. School into Six. ca. 1993 (Box 12)
        - Bradley, Ann. (1995, Mar. 22). Thinking Small. Education Week.
        - Gonzalez, David. A Bridge from Hope to Social Action. New York Times. Undated
      - Press releases and summaries, 1992-1993, undated
      - Planning documents, 1992-1995, undated
      - Correspondence, 1992-1996, undated
        - General, 1992-1996, undated
        - With Chancellors Fernandez and Cortines, 1992-1995
        - On physical space, 1992-1996
        - On problems with buildings, 1994-1996
        - On graduation requirements, 1995, undated
      - Notes by Meier, 1994, undated
    - Annenberg Grant and New York Networks for School Renewal (NYNSR), 1993-2007, undated
      - Articles, 1994-2007, undated
        - Richardson, Lynda. (1994, Sept. 4). Taking Change from Classroom to Central Office. New York Times., 4 copies
        - Richardson, Lynda. (1994, Sept. 4). Taking Change from Classroom to Central Office. New York Times., 4 copies (Box 3)
        - Celis, William. (1994, Sept. 22). New York Receives $100 Million Gift for 50 New Schools. Daily News (p. 20)., 2 copies (Box 12)
        - (1994, Sept. 22). New Schools Foundation Offers $50M to Shake Up System. New York Newsday (p. A3).
          Headline only
        - Thrush, Glenn. (1994, Sept.). Visionaries in Exile: NYC's Small-School Movement. Metropolis (pp. 53-57). (Box 3)
        - Siegel, Jessica. (1994, Nov. 14). A Socialist Leads Unlikely Coalition to Reinvent Schools. New York Observer., 2 copies (Box 12)
        - Porto, Ana González and Warren Sprouse. (1994, Nov.). Hope for Our Children's Future. Upper West Side Current, volume 1, number 1 (pp. 1, 4). (Box 3)
        - Powell, Michael and Liz Willen. A Class Gift: $50M Grant Helps Build New Schools, ca. 1994 (Box 12)
        - Teltsch, Kathleen. Foundation Grant Sought to Start 50 Small Schools. New York Times (p. B3), ca. 1994 (Box 3)
        - Dillon, Sam and Joseph Berger. (1995, May 22). New Schools Seeking Small Miracles. New York Times, volume 144, number 50,069 (pp. A1, B4). (Box 12)
        - Firestone, David. (1995, May 24). When Teachers Unite to Run School. New York Times (p. A1, B6). (Box 3)
        - (1995, May 25). Friction Over Experimental Academies Rises Along with Change. New York Times, second page only.
        - Board of Ed Sees No Evil. 1996, Jan. 2 (Box 12)
        - McAdoo, Maisie. (1997, Mar. 26). Benevolence as a Mixed Blessing: Reformers, Chancellor Lock Horns Over Largesse. Village Voice.
        - Siegel, Jessica. (2007, Apr. 10). Small Order. Village Voice.
        - Finder, Alan. 60 Schools Will Be Exempt from Range of Regulations. Undated
      - Proposal to the Annenberg Foundation, undated
      - Materials on testing, undated
      - Press releases and statements, 1993-1995, undated
      - Schedules, meeting notes, and agendas, 1994-1997, undated
      - Correspondence with Annenberg Institute, 1994-2004
      - Education Through Music program description and Comeau resume, 1994
    - Coalition of Essential Schools (CES), 1983-2008
      - Planning documents and correspondence, 1983-1996
      - Events and projects, 1999-2008
      - Memorandum on restructuring the New York City Board of Education, 1994
  - Mission Hill School, 1996-2008, undated (Box 12)
    - Articles, 1996-2003
      - Avenoso, Karen. (1996, July 4). Reformer Eyes Boston for a New Pilot School. Boston Globe, volume 250, number 4 (pp. 1, 13). (Box 3)
      - Steinberg, Jacques. (1996, Oct. 5). Top Educator is Leaving to Open School in Boston. New York Times (p. 27)., 2 copies
      - Van Dorn, Betsy. (1997, July 23). Shaking up the System. Family Education Network. (Box 12)
      - Cohen, Muriel. (1997, Sept. 28). Mission Hill School's Curriculum: Inclusion, Democracy, Respect. Boston Globe (pp. 1, 7)., 4 copies (Box 12)
      - Cohen, Muriel. (1997, Sept. 28). Mission Hill School's Curriculum: Inclusion, Democracy, Respect. Boston Globe (pp. 1, 7)., 4 copies (Box 3)
      - Sege, Irene. (1999, Jan. 13). Learning Verve: Educator Deborah Meier Fights the Standardization Mentality in her Innovative Roxbury Pilot School. Boston Globe (pp. F1, F4-F5)., 3 copies (Box 12)
      - Sege, Irene. (1999, Jan. 13). Learning Verve: Educator Deborah Meier Fights the Standardization Mentality in her Innovative Roxbury Pilot School. Boston Globe (pp. F1, F4-F5)., 3 copies (Box 3)
      - Pick, Grant. (2000, Sept.). Taking the Road Less Traveled: Authentic Assessment in Other Locales. Catalyst. (Box 12)
      - Winerip, Michael. (2003, June 11). Going for Depth Instead of Prep. New York Times., 4 copies
    - Administrative documents, 1996-2007, undated
      - Planning and History, 1996-1997, undated
        Includes notes, correspondence, building information
      - Governance and Policies, 1998, undated
      - Gates Foundation funding request, 2002
      - Staff and student directories, 1998-1999
      - Staff meeting agendas, 2001-2007, undated
      - Teacher Peer Review Handbook, 2006
    - Correspondence, 1998-2008, undated
      - Correspondence with students and parents, 2000-2008, undated
      - Memos and correspondence with staff and volunteers, 1998-2004, undated
    - Mailings and publications, 1997-2008, undated
      - Brochures, undated
      - Class newsletters, 2000-2001
      - Mailings to parents and parent newsletter, 2000-2005
      - Mission Hill News, 1997-2008
        Incomplete run
        - Volume 1, 1997-1998
        - Volume 2, 1998-1999
        - Volume 3, 1999-2000
        - Volume 4, 2000-2001
        - Volume 5, 2001-2002
        - Volume 7-8, 2004-2005
        - Volume 9, 2005-2006
        - Volume 10, 2006-2007
        - Volume 11, 2007-2008
        - Volume 12, 2008
        - Play sections, undated
      - Francis W. Parker Friday Announcements and Mission Hill News photocopies from Andy Hrycyna, 1998-2002
        Includes a letter from Andy Hrycyna
      - Programs for graduation and anniversary, 2006-2007 (Box 13)
    - Student work, 2001-2007, undated
      - Blank Assignments, 2001, undated
      - Student memory books, 2001-2007
      - Student portfolio work and application essay, undated
    - Miscellaneous, 2000-2006, undated
      - Student reading, writing, and exit interview assessments, 2000-2001
      - Evaluations of the school and its staff, 2001-2005
      - Cards and notes sent to Meier on her retirement, 2005
      - Recognitions for Meier's work at Mission Hill, 2005
      - Speech by Linda Nathan on Boston Pilot Schools, 2000
      - Miscellaneous, 2006, undated
  - Conferences and speaking engagements, 1981-2009, undated (Box 13)
    After timeline, arranged chronologically
    - Timeline, 1981-1985
    - Head Start Basic Educational Skills National Conference on Curriculum and Parent Involvement in Bathesda, Maryland, 1981, Feb. 9-11
      Includes conference folder
    - Early Childhood Education Council of New York City Annual Conference in New York City, 1982, Mar. 13
    - Truth-and-Testing Conference, 1982, Apr. 24
      Includes agenda
    - Citizen Heritage Center Democracy in America Conference '82, 1982
    - Valuing Teaching: A Public Forum, 1986, Feb. 2
    - Solving the Crisis in Education: Everybody's Problem, the Fifth Conference, 1987, Mar. 21
      Includes registration form and program
    - Seattle Schools Administrator's Retreat, 1987, Aug. 25-26
    - NAACP Legal Defense and Educational Fund dinner, 1987, Dec. 10
      Includes invitation
    - American Federation of Teachers Convention, 1988, July 1-6
    - Sarah's Daughters book signing sponsored by Women's American ORT, 1988, Nov. 17
    - Socialist Scholars Conference, 1980s
      Includes registration form
    - International Conference of Education for Democracy in a Multicultural Society in Jerusalem, Israel, 1993, June
      Includes correspondence, list of participants, and notes
      See also: Can We Impose a Democratic Education on Kids? Speech in Israel
    - New Haven School System Gala Dinner and Awards Ceremony, 1994
    - AERA event in San Francisco, 1995, Apr. 18-22
      Includes two itineraries
    - The Leadership Forum, 1995, Spring
      Includes registration packet
    - 13th Annual International Conference: Magnet Schools, Bridges to the 21st Century in San Jose, California, 1995, May 2-5
      Includes registration booklet
    - Harvard Education Forum, 1995, May 10 (Box 1)
      Includes poster
    - Great Neck Public Schools Superintendent's Conference Day: Raising Expectations of Student Achievement, 1995, Nov. 7 (Box 13)
      See also: Great Neck Public Schools Superintendent's Conference Day keynote address by Meier titled Raising Expectations of Student Achievement, VHS
    - A Vision for Our Children: Transforming Public Education for a Democratic Society in Ann Arbor, Michigan, 1995, Dec. 9
      Includes program and poster
    - Can All Kids Go to Good Schools? lecture by Meier in Houston, Texas, 1996, Feb. 7
      Includes flyer
    - State Superintendent's Premier Speakers Series, lecture by Meier in Chicago, Illinois, 1996, Mar. 7
      Includes flyer and program
    - From Mann to Meier: 200 Years of Educational Reform at Antioch College in Yellow Springs, Ohio, 1996
    - Wheelock College Convocation, 1996, Sept. 11
    - 8th national Finding Better Ways conference in Cambridge, Massachusetts, 1997, Mar. 17-20
    - Brodie Family Lecture at Bowdoin College in Brunswick, Maine, 1998, Apr. 30 (Box 13)
      - Brodie Family Inaugural Lecture poster, 1998, Apr. 30 (Box 1)
    - Reach Out to Schools: Social Competency Program, 10th Anniversary Celebration at Wellesley College, 1998, May 12 (Box 13)
    - A Celebration of the Life and Work of Theodore R. Sizer at Brown University in Providence, Rhode Island, 1999, Apr. 29-30
    - Changing Lives: a Conference on Relational Education, 1999, May 8
    - ACA/NES 2000 Spring Conference, 2000, Mar. 24-26
    - Upper Valley Teacher Institute: A Celebration of Teachers in Lebanon, New Hampshire, 2002, Apr. 28
      Includes two programs
    - Annual Conference of Brookings Papers on Education Policy: The Teachers We Need, 2003, May 21-22
    - Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr. Business & Professional Breakfast Issue Paper Series in Charleston, South Carolina, 2003, Sept. 30
    - Small Is Not Enough: Creating High Achieving Schools for All Students conference in Portland, Oregon, 2004, Jan. 30-31
    - Carnegie: Teachers for a New Era retreat at the University of Washington, 2004, Jan. 30
      Includes retreat folder
    - The 2nd International Summit for Leadership in Education: Integrity & Interdependence in Boston, Massachusetts, 2004, Nov. 4-6
    - Coalition of Essential Schools Fall Forum: Equitable Schools for a New Democracy in San Francisco, California, 2004, Nov. 11-13
    - A Conversation with Visionary Educators at Brandeis University, 2004, Nov. 18
    - Building Collaborations to Change Our Organizations and the World: Systems Thinking in Action in Cambridge, Massachusetts, 2004, Dec. 1-3
      Includes list of keynote speakers
    - The Master of Arts in Teaching Program Celebration, 2005, June 18
    - Eighth Annual National Principals Leadership Institute in New York City, 2005, July 9-16
    - Pi Lambda Theta Leadership Conference in New Orleans, Louisiana, 2005, July 28-31
      Includes program and schedule
    - International Conference in Jewish Education in Jerusalem; Israel, Turkey, and Greece trip, 2006, June-July
      Includes correspondence, flight bookings, tourist information, and conference program
    - Progressive Education Network Conference, 2006, Oct. 14
    - Algebra Project and Columbia School of Journalism Brainstorm Session Education Conference, 2007, Mar. 29-31
      Includes participant biographies
    - World Conference on Transformation of Classroom Teaching in Shanghai, China, 2007, May-June
      Includes correspondence, flight bookings, itineraries, and conference folders
      See also: Shanghai Racquet Club CD on an architectural project by Paul Willen
    - The School on the Side of the Child conference in Moscow, Russia, 2007, Sept.
      Includes flight bookings, conference folder, article, and Russian publications
    - Lecture in Zurich, Switzerland, 2007, Oct. 26
      Includes correspondence, flight bookings, and programs
    - Science Inquiry: Theme and Variations conference at the City College of New York, 2007, Oct. 27
    - In Defense of Childhood meeting, 2007, Oct. 31and 2007, Dec. 12
      Includes meeting minutes
    - Eastern Michigan University 2007-2008 Speaker Series, 2008, Feb. 7
      Includes brochure and folder of materials related to Meier's lecture
    - Public School Education Reform in an Era of Accountability Politics at Grinnell College, 2008, Feb. 19-21
    - Distinguished Lecturer Series, 2008, Mar. 19
    - AERA Annual Meeting, 2008, Mar. 24-28
      Includes program supplement, agenda, and other materials
    - 62nd Annual Meeting of Education Reporters, Writers and Editors, 2008, Apr. 30-May 2
      Includes meeting program and empty folder
    - 5th Annual AERO Conference, Moving from Ideas to Practices; 2008, June 26-29
    - Education Minnesota Professional Conference, 2008, Oct. 16-17
    - University of Manitoba Faculty of Education Distinguished Lecture Series, 2008, Oct. 23 (Box 13)
      - University of Manitoba Faculty of Education Distinguished Lecture posters, 2008, Oct. 23, Two posters (Box 1)
    - The Engaged Learner in Winnipeg, Canada, 2008, Oct. 23-24 (Box 13)
    - School of Education Centennial Symposium and Celebration at Indiana University in Bloomington, Indiana, 2008, Nov. 16-17& 20
    - The Niemeyer Series in New York City, 2009, Jan. 21
    - Advanced Leadership Initiative at Harvard University, 2009, Mar. 12-14
      Includes agendas
    - Education Writers Association 62nd National Seminar, 2009, Apr. 30-May 2
      Includes participants list
    - Reshaping of Public Education workshops, undated
      Includes two brochures
  - Other, 1983-2005, undated (Box 13)
    - Committee of Correspondence on the Future of Public Education, 1983-1984, undated
      - Organizing documents, manifesto drafts, and agendas, 1983-1984, undated
      - Newsletter, 1983-1984, undated
      - Session summary, contact list, workshop description, and miscellaneous, 1983, undated
    - Princeton Review Portfolio Scholarship Program Technical Trade, 1993-1994
      Includes correspondence and student application
    - New England Small Schools Network Design Week, 2001, Aug. 12-17, Readings
    - Education course taught by Meier at Stanford University, 2003-2004, undated (Box 13)
      - Correspondence on planning, syllabus, and student list, 2003-2004, undated
        Includes syllabus for previous course taught by Meier
      - Correspondence with students, 2004
      - Student assignments, 2004
    - Forum on Education and Democracy memorandum, statements, and paper by CPESS teacher, 2003-2005, undated
- Honors and awards, 1980-2009, undated (Box 13)
  - MacArthur Fellowship, 1985-1988, undated (Box 13)
    - Recommendation letters, 1985-1986
    - Binder of recommendations, resumes, articles, etc., 1985, undated
    - Award announcement, 1987
    - Articles on Meier winning the award, 1987-1988, undated, (1 folder)
      - Crawford, Jan. (1987, Jun. 16). MacArthur Fellowships to 32: U. of C. Alumnus is 1st Public School Teacher Honored. Chicago Tribune., 3 copies
      - Moss, Desda. (1987, Jun. 16). Giving People 'with Promise' Their Big Shot. USA Today., 3 copies (Box 3)
      - Slagle, Alton. (1987, Jun. 16). Teacher Gets 300G for Big Effort. Daily News., 3 copies
      - Slagle, Alton. (1987, Jun. 16). Teacher Gets 300G for Big Effort. Daily News., 3 copies (Box 13)
      - Teltsch, Kathleen. (1987, Jun. 16). An East Harlem Citadel Where Openness Rules. New York Times., 9 copies